<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://andybromberg.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://andybromberg.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-14T14:57:15-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Andy Bromberg</title><subtitle>Ways of Looking.</subtitle><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><entry><title type="html">Try just one fragrance-free month</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/fragrance-free" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Try just one fragrance-free month" /><published>2024-10-11T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-10-11T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/fragrance-free</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/fragrance-free"><![CDATA[<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/fragrance-free/fragrances-400-2196c4eed.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/fragrance-free/fragrances-600-2196c4eed.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/fragrance-free/fragrances-800-2196c4eed.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/fragrance-free/fragrances-1000-2196c4eed.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/fragrance-free/fragrances-400-38465bcd3.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/fragrance-free/fragrances-600-38465bcd3.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/fragrance-free/fragrances-800-38465bcd3.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/fragrance-free/fragrances-1000-38465bcd3.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/fragrance-free/fragrances-800-38465bcd3.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<p>In 2018, I was <em>always</em> at least a little congested and sniffly. I had some brain fog. I got headaches more than I felt like I should.</p>

<p>I chalked it up to startup stress and lots of travel.</p>

<p>Then, my friend Andrew Herr at <a href="https://fount.bio/">Fount</a> told me to go entirely fragrance-free for a month.</p>

<p>He’s brilliant, and I love experimenting. So I did it.</p>

<p>Two days in, I started to wonder if I was feeling a difference.</p>

<p>A week in, I was sure something was going on.</p>

<p>A week after that, I knew I was never going back.</p>

<p>Now, six years out, I believe it’s one of the most impactful health changes I’ve ever made. It cleared up the constant low-level congestion, sniffles, headaches, brain fog — all of it.</p>

<p>At this point, I’ve lost track of how many people I’ve recommended this to who say the same.</p>

<p>Here’s the experiement I think <em>everyone</em> should try:</p>

<p><span class="highlighter"><strong>Go entirely fragrance-free for a month.</strong></span> That means:</p>
<ul>
  <li>unscented deoderant</li>
  <li>unscented laundry detergent and dryer sheets</li>
  <li>unscented hand wash</li>
  <li>unscented cleaning supplies</li>
  <li>unscented body wash, shampoo, and conditioner</li>
  <li>unscented lotion</li>
  <li>no scented candles</li>
  <li>no perfume or cologne</li>
  <li>no air freshners</li>
  <li>and no scented trash bags or anything else — you’ll realize quickly if you missed anything</li>
</ul>

<p>Sound overwhelming? It’s not that bad. <a href="https://dolightwork.com/file/lightwork-big-two">This guide</a> has a list of products to swap / buy — just scroll to the “Eliminating Fragrances” page.</p>

<p>Our bodies are simply not meant to be exposed to so many fragrances — especially artificial ones.</p>

<p>Give it a shot. I bet you’ll notice a difference.</p>

<hr class="end-of-article-divider" />

<h2 class="no_toc">Looking for more to read?</h2>

<nav class="post-navigation">
  <div class="prev-post">
    
    <a href="/startup-pr-rulebook">
    
    <div class="post-nav-header"><i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-left post-nav-arrow"></i> Previous post</div>
    
    </a>
    
    
      <a href="/startup-pr-rulebook">Startup PR, Part I: the rules of the game</a>
    
  </div>
  <div class="next-post">
    <div class="post-nav-header">
        
        Next post <i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-right post-nav-arrow"></i>
        
    </div>
    
        <em>You're at the latest post already!</em>
    
  </div>
</nav>

<div>
    <p>Want to hear about new essays? Subscribe to my roughly-monthly <a href="https://andybromberg.substack.com">newsletter</a> recapping my recent writing and things I'm enjoying:</p>
    <div class="substack">
        <iframe src="https://andybromberg.substack.com/embed" width="480" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>
    </div>

    <p>And I'd love to hear from you directly: <a href="mailto:andy@andybromberg.com">andy@andybromberg.com</a></p>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Everyone should try one month without fragrances. Here's how it went for me.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/fragrance-free.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/fragrance-free.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Startup PR, Part I: the rules of the game</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/startup-pr-rulebook" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Startup PR, Part I: the rules of the game" /><published>2024-10-09T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-10-09T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/startup-pr-rulebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/startup-pr-rulebook"><![CDATA[<h2 class="no_toc" id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p><strong>This post is the rulebook I wish someone handed me earlier in my career about PR and working with journalists.</strong></p>

<p>You wouldn’t expect to do well playing Settlers of Catan — or even be able to talk strategy — without first reading the rulebook, and the same is true for doing PR. It’s a complicated game with idiosyncratic rules.</p>

<p>This post is about those rules: how to interact with journalists, the jargon you need to know, and key mental models.</p>

<p>If all you’re looking for is press coverage for your upcoming launch: close this page, reach out to your friends and investors asking for PR firm recommendations, and go hire the best one. (Or wait for Part II, where I cover how I’d get that coverage myself.)</p>

<p>But if you want to <em>understand the rules</em> of the peculiar, opaque game of business journalism — so that you can then play the game well — read on. This post will be a shortcut for you (a long shortcut, but a shortcut nonetheless!).</p>

<p>Also: this isn’t about the hard work of figuring out your story, goals, and positioning — which are the most important parts of doing PR well. I assume you’ve got that sorted out, and now you’re trying to figure out how to use traditional media to amplify those ideas.</p>

<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/printing-400-434235518.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/printing-600-434235518.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/printing-800-434235518.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/printing-1000-434235518.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/printing-400-5cd79b448.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/printing-600-5cd79b448.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/printing-800-5cd79b448.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/printing-1000-5cd79b448.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/printing-800-5cd79b448.png" width="1892" height="512" /></picture>

<h2 id="why-learn-the-game-of-pr">Why learn the game of PR?</h2>

<p>I’ve found traditional media coverage to be tremendously useful.</p>

<p>Many team members, customers, and investors have found my companies thanks to our PR efforts. And the coverage isn’t just great for top-of-funnel — it also helps close people once they’re interested. It can impact how your brand is perceived in the market, reach specific audiences, and give you the collateral and validation to close deals, investors, hires, and more.</p>

<p>Done right, <em>PR actually does work</em> — and is worth the effort and expense.</p>

<p>And I’m not the only one who thinks this.</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/chesky-400-66e9b3632.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/chesky-600-66e9b3632.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/chesky-800-66e9b3632.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/chesky-1000-66e9b3632.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/chesky-400-e1b05b7ee.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/chesky-600-e1b05b7ee.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/chesky-800-e1b05b7ee.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/chesky-1000-e1b05b7ee.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/chesky-800-e1b05b7ee.png" width="1236" height="412" /></picture>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/gurley-400-4433c840b.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/gurley-600-4433c840b.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/gurley-800-4433c840b.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/gurley-1000-4433c840b.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/gurley-400-f1c5bf82c.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/gurley-600-f1c5bf82c.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/gurley-800-f1c5bf82c.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/gurley-1000-f1c5bf82c.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/gurley-800-f1c5bf82c.png" width="1232" height="924" /></picture>

<p>Plus: it’s just <em>really interesting</em>. At some level — whether you like it or not — the world runs on media. For better or for worse, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_Estate">“fourth estate”</a> governs how the vast majority of people build their beliefs and learn about what’s happening around them.</p>

<p>And yet I’ve found many leaders simply haven’t taken the time to learn how it works. I find it a game worth learning — and playing.</p>

<h2 id="a-note-on-going-direct">A note on “Going Direct”</h2>

<p>As of publish time (late 2024), we’re in the age of “going direct” — an approach to communications popularized by Andreessen Horowitz and <a href="https://www.getflack.com/p/go-direct-the-manifesto">Lulu Cheng Meservey</a>. It broadly advocates for owning your communications, minimizing engagement with traditional media, and focusing on more-direct, less-intermediated channels.</p>

<p>I love this strategy.</p>

<p>But I also believe that for many companies, there’s still a strong case for more traditional PR and media engagement — whether alongside a “go direct” strategy or not.</p>

<p>This post is not about whether you should go direct (you probably should). This post is about the traditional side of the game — which will affect you whether you like it or not.</p>

<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/boardgame-400-6818e55f0.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/boardgame-600-6818e55f0.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/boardgame-800-6818e55f0.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/boardgame-1000-6818e55f0.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/boardgame-400-646e13896.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/boardgame-600-646e13896.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/boardgame-800-646e13896.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/boardgame-1000-646e13896.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/boardgame-800-646e13896.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<h2 id="game-terminology--basic-rules">Game terminology &amp; basic rules</h2>

<p>Before you learn the rules and norms, you need to speak the language.</p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="what-is-pr">What is “PR?”</h3>

<p>Technically, Public Relations (PR) is a broad category, including media relations, messaging strategy, owned content, crisis communications, and more.</p>

<p>But many people think of PR as just “media relations,” which is mostly an innuendo for “getting articles written about us.” That’s what this post is about.</p>

<p>Other people refer to the broader category as “Communications” or “Strategic Comms.”</p>

<p>Often, <em>internally</em> at a company, you’ll have a Communications function (and perhaps, if you’re big enough, sub-functions like Corporate Comms, Product Comms, Internal Comms, Executive Comms…). And then <em>externally,</em> you’ll hire “PR” firms.</p>

<p>None of this really matters, in my opinion, and you can argue about the ever-changing definitions all day. I’ll use several of these terms interchangeably in this post, but mainly lean on “PR.”</p>

<p>Ultimately, this whole post is about the art and science of interacting with journalists and getting media coverage. That’s probably more accurately referred to as “Media Relations,” but few have heard that term, so “PR” it is!</p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="types-of-stories-publications-and-mentions">Types of stories, publications, and mentions</h3>

<p>There are generally three types of stories:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Trend pieces:</strong> these are pieces that are not about a specific company or piece of news, but rather about a broader trend (<em>“how AI startups are contending with the chip shortage”</em>)</li>
  <li><strong>News articles:</strong> these are about a specific event — a fundraise, a hire, an acquisition, etc.</li>
  <li><strong>Profile pieces:</strong> these are in-depth articles about a company or person. Sometimes they are anchored in a piece of news, but they go beyond the news to more deeply profile the subject.</li>
</ul>

<p>Those are listed in order of difficulty to get yourself into. Journalists always want to cover trends, and if you’re relevant to the trend, you can try to insert yourself. But of course, you have to have a good enough relationship with the reporter to know they’re writing the piece — or you have to be so relevant to the trend that they can’t help but reach out to you.</p>

<p>They’re a little more skeptical of covering news. And they’re most hesitant to do a big profile story (there are also simply fewer reporters who have the latitude or responsibility to write those sorts of pieces).</p>

<p>Aside from the three types of <em>stories</em>, there are different types of <em>publications</em>. Broadly, the ones that are relevant to tech startups fall into:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Trade publications / industry publications:</strong> these are specific to the industry your company is addressing. For logistics: FreightWaves. For advertising: AdWeek. For legal: Law360. For crypto: Coindesk. And so on… (there are usually several big ones in each industry)</li>
  <li><strong>Tech / startup media:</strong> TechCrunch, The Verge, etc.</li>
  <li><strong>Mainstream media:</strong> WSJ, NYT, CNBC, etc.</li>
</ul>

<p>These are <em>also</em> listed in order of difficulty. It’s easiest to get covered in a trade publication, harder in the tech / startup media, and hardest in the mainstream media.</p>

<p>So: profile piece in the mainstream media? Hardest type of story to pull off. Being in a trend piece in a trade publication? Easiest one.</p>

<p>And that brings us to a final division of media participation: the three ways you or your startup can be covered/mentioned in the piece:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Subject:</strong> most of this guide is going to cover being the subject of the story. That means being one of the featured examples in a trend piece, or the source of the news in a news article, or the subject of a profile piece.</li>
  <li><strong>Ancillary mention:</strong> sometimes, your startup will be mentioned in a piece about something else — perhaps a story about a venture fund that happened to invest in you or in a competitor, or in a newsletter or “rollup.” You often will not even hear from the journalist before this happens.</li>
  <li><strong>Expert/quote:</strong> you can be quoted by the journalist in a story that’s not about you — but where they see you as an expert.</li>
</ul>

<p>That last category is a nice piece of “bonus” coverage where your company gets mentioned and you are positioned as a smart person. It usually happens in one of two ways:</p>
<ol>
  <li>You have a relationship with the journalist and they reach out to you about a story they’re writing because they think you’d have genuinely interesting thoughts</li>
  <li>Your PR team (a firm or internal) is <strong>“newsjacking”</strong> — when other news is happening, they reach out to journalists likely to cover it and say “I’m sure you’re writing about Apple’s earnings — our client Jane would have great perspective on that given her business. Want to talk to her?” or even “I’m sure you’re writing about Apple’s earnings — here’s what our client Jane has to say about them: [quote]. Let us know if you’d like to connect with her, or feel free to use that quote.”</li>
</ol>

<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/notebook-400-131f617c4.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/notebook-600-131f617c4.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/notebook-800-131f617c4.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/notebook-1000-131f617c4.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/notebook-400-b811e2bda.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/notebook-600-b811e2bda.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/notebook-800-b811e2bda.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/notebook-1000-b811e2bda.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/notebook-800-b811e2bda.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="on--or-off--the-record">On — or off — the record</h3>

<p>There are three ways you can talk to a reporter: <strong>on the record</strong>, <strong>on background</strong>, or <strong>off the record</strong>. Critically, if you don’t want to be “on the record,” <em>you need to make that agreement with a reporter before you start talking to them.</em> Everything is on the record unless mutually agreed otherwise. This is among the most important rules of dealing with journalists.</p>

<p>The word “mutual” is key there: you can’t just email someone or talk to them and say “this is off the record…” and have it be so. They have to agree.</p>

<p><strong>On the record</strong> means that <em>anything</em> you say can be quoted, attributed to you. When you see “… said Tim Cook, CEO of Apple,” Tim was on the record. Again, this is the default unless mutually agreed-to otherwise.</p>

<p><strong>On background</strong> is a little nebulous. It generally means that what you say <em>can</em> be directly quoted, but <em>not</em> attributed to you by name. When you see “… said a senior executive at Apple,” that executive was “on background.”</p>

<p>The best way to manage being on background is to mutually agree with the reporter that what you’re saying is “on background,” and then agree on a way to characterize you.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You: Ok, and… can I share the next bit with you on background?</p>

  <p>Reporter: Sure</p>

  <p>You: Great. Does it work to attribute it to “a company spokesperson?”</p>

  <p>Reporter: That’s fine with me</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This could be <em>“a company spokesperson,” “a person familiar with the discussions,” “a source close to the matter,” “a senior executive at the company,” “someone who is familiar with Tim’s thinking,”</em> etc.</p>

<p>Anytime you see one of those phrases in a story, it’s because the speaker went on background.</p>

<p>Last, <strong>off the record</strong> means that the information you share cannot be put in the piece at all, and — really, in the strictest sense — should not be written down or repeated to anyone (including the journalist’s colleagues).</p>

<p>The degree of adherence to this rule varies journalist to journalist and outlet to outlet, so I suggest, to be safe, assuming the minimum when deciding what to share off the record: that you will not be named or characterized alongside the information, but that the information might still make it into the piece anyway.</p>

<p>If the information can’t be put in a piece, why would journalists ever want it? Because it gives them clues that can help them figure out who else to call or where else to look while they’re reporting a story.</p>

<p>If it’s a good piece of information shared off the record, they’ll probably start calling around to other people who might have the same info and try to get them to say it on background or on the record (but, if adhering to strict ethics, without disclosing that they already know it).</p>

<p>Is your head spinning yet? It goes even deeper with “not for attribution” or “with quote checks” or “on deep background” — but we don’t need to get into those.</p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="embargoes-and-exclusives">Embargoes and Exclusives</h3>

<p>When trying to get coverage, <strong>embargoes</strong> and <strong>exclusives</strong> are two powerful tools.</p>

<p>An <strong>embargo</strong> is an agreement between you and a reporter that they will not publish anything about your news until a certain date and time. Just like going on background or off the record, <em>this must be agreed to before you share the information.</em> If you share information before agreeing, it is not “under embargo.”</p>

<p>This leads to a challenging situation: you want to get a reporter excited and on the phone to hear the pitch from you, but you don’t want to tell them what the news is. So you’re left with something like:</p>

<div class="mac-window imessage-popup">
    <div class="mac-toolbar">
      <div class="mac-buttons">
        <span class="mac-button close"></span>
        <span class="mac-button minimize"></span>
        <span class="mac-button maximize"></span>
      </div>
      <div class="toolbar-title">Chat</div>
    </div>
    <div class="imessage-scroll-container">
        <div class="imessage">
        
            
            <p class="from-me">We’ve got some really exciting news at Acme Corp. I’d love to share with you. Could you agree to an embargo for next Thursday at 9am ET?</p>
            
        
        </div>
    </div>
</div>

<p>If you don’t have a good existing relationship, or that pitch isn’t otherwise very newsworthy (more on that term in a second), they might just ignore it. You can take a shot just putting the news in the outreach and <em>request</em> an embargo, but you have to be aware that they might decide to just publish it before the embargo date, since it was never agreed to.</p>

<p>They might agree to the embargo to hear the pitch. Or, they might reply:</p>

<div class="mac-window imessage-popup">
    <div class="mac-toolbar">
      <div class="mac-buttons">
        <span class="mac-button close"></span>
        <span class="mac-button minimize"></span>
        <span class="mac-button maximize"></span>
      </div>
      <div class="toolbar-title">Chat</div>
    </div>
    <div class="imessage-scroll-container">
        <div class="imessage">
        
            
            <p class="from-me">We’ve got some really exciting news at Acme Corp. I’d love to share with you. Could you agree to an embargo for next Thursday at 9am ET?</p>
            
        
            
            <p class="from-them">Is this an exclusive?</p>
            
        
        </div>
    </div>
</div>

<p>An <strong>exclusive</strong> means that you are only giving the information to a single journalist or outlet in advance of the news breaking. This is what reporters want — they don’t want to be one of many covering the same story with the same information. When we get further, we’ll see that this can be a major point of leverage for getting coverage.</p>

<p>If you want a top-tier publication to cover something, you often have to give them an exclusive.</p>

<p>There are also variations on this — you could try to get by with not-quite-a-full-exclusive, but a <strong>partial exclusive</strong>. Perhaps: <em>“the story isn’t an exclusive, but I could give you an exclusive interview with the lead investor”</em> (i.e. you will pitch the story to several outlets, but won’t set the lead investor up with anyone else). Or <em>“the story isn’t an exclusive, but we can exclusively give you some metrics on pre-launch signups”</em> (i.e. no other outlets will get those numbers in advance).</p>

<p>After the news breaks — at the embargo time, or whenever it comes out if an embargo isn’t set — you’re free to talk to whoever you want and seek out <strong>follow-on coverage</strong>. There’s no more exclusivity at that point. But before then, if you agree to an exclusive, you can’t talk to anyone else.</p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="whats-newsworthy">What’s “Newsworthy?”</h3>

<p>Perhaps the most important concept for founders to understand: reporters will only cover stories that are <strong>newsworthy.</strong></p>

<p>This means, tautologically, exactly what it sounds like: newspeople working for news publications will only cover news that deserves to be in the news.</p>

<p>But <em>what</em> is newsworthy? How can you make something seem newsworthy to a reporter? What “deserves to be in the news?”</p>

<p><strong>It needs to be content that readers of that publication will be interested to read, in the journalist (and their editor’s) subjective opinion.</strong> To get a sense of what’s newsworthy for a specific journalist or publication, you can simply check out what they’ve published historically.</p>

<p>Newsworthiness is not a binary. It’s about stacking as much as you can to push the story over the newsworthy line.</p>

<p>Here are some things that can contribute to a story being newsworthy:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Objective not subjective</li>
  <li>Big names</li>
  <li>Quantitative</li>
  <li>Publication-specific context</li>
  <li>Relationships</li>
  <li>Your pitch</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Objective not subjective:</strong> it’s not newsworthy to say <em>“the best new CRM just launched”</em> — that’s just an opinion, and journalists aren’t in the business of covering your opinion about your business. <em>“The first CRM built for the construction industry?”</em> More objective, better chance of getting covered.</p>

<p><strong>Big names:</strong> if there’s a company that everyone cares about, most things having to do with that company are instantly newsworthy.</p>

<p>For example: every feature Facebook launches gets coverage in tech blogs, because Facebook itself is inherently newsworthy. Your fledgling social network’s new features are not inherently newsworthy (even if they’re better than Facebook’s!).</p>

<p>Another example: if Sequoia Capital does a deal, that fundraise will get coverage in startup publications, because Sequoia itself is inherently newsworthy. A fundraise from a smaller VC may not.</p>

<p><strong>Quantitative:</strong> the more compelling numbers you can share, the more newsworthy your pitch is. <em>“We’re growing fast!”</em> doesn’t do much for you; <em>“we’re adding 20% more customers per day than [incumbent] — more than 60 a day!”</em> is catnip (notice that touches both “quantitative” and “big names”).</p>

<p><strong>Publication-specific context:</strong> think about the readers of the publication you’re pitching. If it’s TechCrunch, maybe the investors in the fundraising round are the most compelling thing. If it’s Bloomberg, maybe it’s how you’re beating the incumbents. If it’s a trade publication, maybe it’s the details of your product innovation.</p>

<p><strong>Relationships:</strong> I’ll get to this more later, but your relationship with the reporter can push the balance of the newsworthiness. If they see you as a valuable source or someone they want to build a good relationship with, they are more likely to say something otherwise-borderline is newsworthy (although it still has to make it past the editors!).</p>

<p><strong>Your pitch:</strong> you should, of course, be a pro at pitching your company. You’ve gotten people to join your team, perhaps raised money, and convinced customers to sign up. At the end of the day, if you can convince a journalist that your company or the news is groundbreaking and needs to be covered for their audience… you’ve got a newsworthy story. So: flex that persuasive muscle.</p>

<p>Really, there’s so much more than this. The best question to ask is the general one: why will readers care?</p>

<p>Reporters want to cover things that <em>feel like</em> — and <em>are</em> — actually interesting news. So figure out what in your story makes it so.</p>

<p><em>“Yet another SaaS company raised a seed round”</em> = not interesting by itself. Why should people care?</p>

<p>If you read the stories that get written, you’ll almost always see some sort of “hook” that tells the reader why they should care about the story. Think about what that looks like for you and your news.</p>

<p>My most frequent feedback to founders asking for PR advice: <em>“what you’re pitching is not newsworthy, even thought it feels like the most important thing in the world to you. Figure out why the reporter should care, or otherwise don’t waste time trying to get it covered.”</em></p>

<p>I can’t overstate how important the idea of newsworthiness is to getting coverage. If the reporter and their editor don’t think your story is newsworthy, it won’t get covered. Simple as that.</p>

<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/reporter-400-1d95b1638.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/reporter-600-1d95b1638.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/reporter-800-1d95b1638.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/reporter-1000-1d95b1638.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/reporter-400-a56990c92.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/reporter-600-a56990c92.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/reporter-800-a56990c92.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/reporter-1000-a56990c92.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/reporter-800-a56990c92.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<h2 id="strategically-interacting-with-journalists">Strategically interacting with journalists</h2>

<p>There’s an art to building and maintaining relationships with journalists. This is one of the things that separates truly exceptional PR people from the merely good ones.</p>

<p>I find these relationships really interesting, especially in a time where the industry/media relationship as a whole is getting rocky (the pendulum tends to swing over the course of decades…).</p>

<p>Here are a few principles to consider:</p>

<p><span class="highlighter"><strong>Journalists are just people like you</strong></span> — there’s a lot of talk in tech these days about the evils of journalism, and <a href="https://x.com/PalmerLuckey/status/1533637324034101248">in some cases</a>, for very good reason. But at the end of the day, individual journalists are just plain ol’ human beings.</p>

<p>Many founders feel like they need to give stiff, tightly-scripted pitches to journalists. But, at their core, journalists want the same things everyone else does: enjoyable conversations, pleasant relationships, and not being yelled at.</p>

<p>They also listen to pitches <em>all day.</em> They have a finely tuned sense for when you’re just giving a spiel. And (as with any conversation) that’s fine <em>sometimes</em>. But if it’s the whole conversation, they probably won’t leave with a warm fuzzy feeling.</p>

<p>And related to that: they’re good at sniffing bullshit. First of all: they hear a lot of it. But second: if they suspect bullshit, <em>their job is literally to spend the entire day calling as many people as they can to find out if it’s true or not.</em> (Because them being bullshitted and then finding out makes for an awfully good story — for them, not for you.)</p>

<p>So most of all, when you’re talking to them, remember that they’re people too. It sounds silly, but I’ve seen far too many founders fail to get coverage — or worse — by treating journalists like story-writing machines and nothing more.</p>

<p><span class="highlighter"><strong>… but they (mostly) aren’t your friends</strong></span> — with the above said… by default, they aren’t your friend. They’re a business relationship. You may be <em>friendly</em> with them, but you need to remember their incentives.</p>

<p>In a sense, it’s like your relationship with your direct competitors’ CEOs.</p>

<p>Friendly? Sometimes! Will you talk shop with them? Sure. Are there ways you can help each other and build a relationship? Yep. But you also need to remember that if you share your recent big insight or customer feedback, it’s probably going to end up on <em>their</em> product roadmap too.</p>

<p>Journalists are the same. They’re <em>mostly</em> not out to screw you (although some are). But if you give them something too good, they won’t hesitate. That’s because…</p>

<p><span class="highlighter"><strong>They’re doing expected value math</strong></span> — by default, most journalists want to retain a neutral/positive relationship with you.</p>

<p>This is because they get rewarded (career-wise) for <strong>scoops</strong> — being the first to break a piece of news that others haven’t found yet. So they want to be the person you call when you have news. That doesn’t mean they’ll go overboard on positivity, but does means they (again, mostly) won’t just be randomly negative for little gain.</p>

<p><em>But,</em> if an opportunity to write big, splashy negative stories presents itself, they will quickly decide to do so — because now they see more (career and peer-approval) upside to writing those stories.</p>

<p>The value of writing about your scandal, or the salacious thing you mentioned to them in passing, or the gossip about a competitor you accidentally said on the record becomes <em>greater</em> than the value of keeping you as a friendly source.</p>

<p>This is sometimes called a journalist <strong>burning</strong> you.</p>

<p>It’s a dilemma — sometimes you (usually accidentally) give them something so good that they have to burn you. And this is one place where the dislike of journalists can arise.</p>

<p><span class="highlighter"><strong>It’s an iterated game of agreements</strong></span> — dealing with journalists is a series of agreements, trust, and building a relationship (just like anything else, really).</p>

<p>And — as evidenced by how far we are into this article, basically just covering terminology so far — the game you play with journalists has a lot of very idiosyncratic rules.</p>

<p>The rules aren’t hard-and-fast. It’s not like the second you say something on the record they publish it. You can even say “oh, jeez, sorry — can that be off the record? I shouldn’t have said that.”</p>

<p>If your relationship is good and the expected value calculation is positive for the journalist, they’ll laugh and say “yeah, no problem.”</p>

<p>If the expected value calculation goes the other way, they might say “sorry, I’m going to keep that on the record.”</p>

<p>That’s how life goes when you play games. Keep the long-term game in mind.</p>

<p>(And it goes the other way too: if you lie to a journalist and get caught, you can be sure they’re going to be less friendly in the future.)</p>

<p><span class="highlighter"><strong>They want interesting info</strong></span> — they’re in the business of finding newsworthy stories and writing about them. They don’t want to cover fundraising announcements all day — they want to be doing deeper journalism.</p>

<p>So if you have a piece of information that might be interesting, it can be worth giving it to them. Maybe you’re hearing rumors of an acquisition, or something going on in your industry.</p>

<p>Reaching out and saying “<em>hey, I’m hearing some interesting stuff about [company], thought you might be interested. Can we chat off the record [or on background]?”</em> is a great way to build a relationship (<em>if</em> the information is actually interesting and especially if it’s not purely self-serving.)</p>

<p><span class="highlighter"><strong>They cover what they want to cover</strong></span> — everyone wishes that journalists would just use the quotes they want them to. But… that’s not how it works.</p>

<p>They can slice up your quotes, take pieces, remove the self-promotional part, etc. — so never assume when you give a quote that it will be printed in full (or at all!).</p>

<p>You need to be okay with any fragment coming out.</p>

<p><span class="highlighter"><strong>You’ll make mistakes</strong></span> — it’s like buying a car from a dealership. The car salesman is practicing for the interaction 8 hours a day. You do it once every five years. They’ve got the upper hand.</p>

<p>Journalists live and breathe the rules of the “journalistic engagement game.” You do it occasionally. Hopefully this article helps you do it well — like reading up on negotiating at a dealership — but you’ll still make mistakes every now and then, and probably get screwed a few times. Such is life.</p>

<p><span class="highlighter"><strong>It’s all about the relationships</strong></span> — they call it “media relations” for a reason.</p>

<p>The game of dealing with journalists has its own rules, but at the end of the day, it’s just relationships — same as when you’re raising money, hiring candidates, closing deals…</p>

<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/prfirm-400-e12538c67.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/prfirm-600-e12538c67.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/prfirm-800-e12538c67.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/prfirm-1000-e12538c67.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/prfirm-400-cfb8c7ecc.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/prfirm-600-cfb8c7ecc.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/prfirm-800-cfb8c7ecc.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/prfirm-1000-cfb8c7ecc.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/prfirm-800-cfb8c7ecc.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<h2 id="3rd-party-players-pr-firms">3rd-party players: PR firms</h2>

<p>As discussed above, <strong>Public Relations (PR)</strong> is a broad discipline. But, as we’ve spent this entire article assuming, the term “PR” is often used by founders who really mean <strong>Media Relations.</strong> And <strong>Media Relations</strong> is itself a polite way of saying “getting articles written about us.” And ultimately, that’s usually what founders are talking about when they reference “PR” — it’s what they really want.</p>

<p>Most PR firms — to justify their large retainers, often $10-50k per month — don’t want to be pigeonholed into <em>just</em> Media Relations. That would be too narrow and too measurable. So instead, they insist on doing more than that. It’s a “bundle,” like paying $70/month for cable TV when really all you want and will watch is one channel.</p>

<p>The best PR firms know the demand for media relations, and they won’t accept unbundling their services, nor will they take a one-month engagement just around your upcoming launch — they’ll only sell you the whole shebang, and for a 3-6 month term, or longer.</p>

<p>That’s not to say that PR firms aren’t useful for anything beyond media relations. The other services certainly <em>can</em> be helpful if you’re working with a truly great firm. But what most founders want is media relations, and you gotta pay the price for that…</p>

<p>You have three options for PR: hire a PR firm, do it yourself, or hire internally.</p>

<p>Despite now having a decade-plus of experience dealing with reporters and a bunch of great relationships with many of them, I still think hiring a PR firm is the way to go initially.</p>

<p>(That said: I think most PR firms are pretty bad, unfortunately. You need to find the great ones.)</p>

<p>As you scale, you’ll also build out an internal comms team. But even when that exists, I think most companies — at least those who have decided media coverage is strategic for them — should have an external PR firm as well.</p>

<p>The core reason: in the iterated game of media relations, PR firms will simply have more at-bats with reporters. They have more reasons to call them!</p>

<p>A reporter only wants to hear from you or your in-house flack<label for="sn-1" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-1" class="margin-toggle" /><span class="sidenote">a nickname for PR / comms people.</span> so many times a month. But the PR firm — assuming they have a bunch of relevant clients — will have many reasons to be in touch.</p>

<p>That means they’ll build a deeper relationship with the reporter, they’ll have more reasons for the reporter not to burn them, and they’ll have a broader network of reporters and editors to go to. Plus, they’ll know what people like and don’t like.</p>

<p>(Of course, the PR firm also has their own incentives — they’re an independent actor in the “game.” Unless you’re a marquee client or paying them their highest retainer, they may not always act in your best interests. That might mean pushing another one of their clients more than you, or, in the worst case, screwing you over to preserve a journalist relationship. Again: you need to find the best firms, same as any other role!)</p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="hiring-a-pr-firm">Hiring a PR firm</h3>

<p>Chase down the firms who have delivered great results. The best way, of course, is through friends, fellow founders, or investors who have seen those results.</p>

<p>The other way is to find startups who have done well with PR, and then find their published press releases on <a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/">PRNewswire</a> or similar sites. Very often, you’ll see a “media contact” listed at the bottom of the press release — and it’ll be a PR firm’s email address (usually something like acme@theprfirm.com). Reach out to that firm!</p>

<p>PR firms are experts at messaging and making things sound good — that’s their job — so it can be very hard to assess who is good and who isn’t from the web presence, or even from a first meeting.</p>

<p>Plus, you run into the eternal problem with agencies: the people you talk to are rarely the ones who actually end up working on the account.</p>

<p>In the process of interviewing a PR firm, you need to get the people who will be working on your account on the phone and interview them directly (as a group is fine). Get their ideas and reactions in real-time.</p>

<p>All too often, PR firms will use their senior people to prep really great pitches to potential clients, and then the juniors end up working on the account and never have ideas that are as good.</p>

<p>So, after your first get-to-know-you call, ask for a call with the people who would be active on the account and talk to them.</p>

<p>If they have good ideas, good instincts, and have individually delivered good results — that’s what you’re looking for.</p>

<p>Make sure you ask clear questions — and memorialize the answers in emails or contracts — about exactly how the different people will be involved. Will the senior person be on every weekly call? Or will they just be “overseeing” things?</p>

<p>And then, of course, run some references on them — asking for clients that have worked with the specific team members on your account.</p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="the-cost-of-pr-firms">The cost of PR firms</h3>

<p>The cost of a PR firm varies wildly. You can hire cheap ones, but I’ve found you pretty much get what you pay for.</p>

<p>In general, I’d say good PR firms start around $6-12k per month. The really good ones won’t take a contract for less than $15-20k per month, and even then you’ll be one of their smaller clients.</p>

<p>To get a really top-tier PR firm and have them lavish attention and their best talent on you, you’ll likely be paying $25-50k per month or more — often up to $100k or so, if you’re a later stage company.</p>

<p>(They typically calibrate according to your stage — but those ranges are pretty reflective of what I’ve seen.)</p>

<p>They usually won’t do less than 6 month contracts, or 3 at the minimum. Plus, the first month is typically a “ramp” month where there is little expectation of results.</p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="managing-pr-firms">Managing PR firms</h3>

<p>It is very hard to get PR firms to firmly commit to press coverage outcomes, and, at some level, for good reason. Without being assured of the news events you will have over a 6 month period, they can be caught in a situation where there just isn’t enough news to deliver the promised outcomes.</p>

<p>With that said, you should talk to them about expectations and ask them to put forward a proposal that includes goals — and hold them to those goals every week.</p>

<p>While managing them, there are two things to remember:</p>
<ol>
  <li>They need to be fed content and news! Lots of founders (myself included, at one point) just assume PR firms will generate coverage. But they need the news from you to do so. You know your business and positioning better than anyone, so give them as much to work with as possible. Trends you’re seeing? Upcoming announcements? Partnerships? External news events you have thoughts on? Send them over.</li>
  <li>Don’t be afraid to ask them to swap team members. They hate this, but if you aren’t happy with someone on your account, let the bosses know and request a swap. Sometimes the person just ends up not being a great fit for <em>your</em> business.</li>
</ol>

<p>I have found, over and over again, that partnerships with PR firms tend to be either 1) bad from the beginning (sad), or 2) great for 3-9 months, then they begin to slide downhill and you need to separate or do some sort of hard reset. Stay vigilant and manage to the plan, as you would with anything else.</p>

<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/equanimity-400-b155db9d9.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/equanimity-600-b155db9d9.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/equanimity-800-b155db9d9.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/equanimity-1000-b155db9d9.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/equanimity-400-14e5b078d.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/equanimity-600-14e5b078d.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/equanimity-800-14e5b078d.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/equanimity-1000-14e5b078d.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/equanimity-800-14e5b078d.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<h2 id="equanimity">Equanimity</h2>

<p>There is so much more that could be written about the subject of PR. If there’s anything you’re still wondering, please do <a href="mailto:andy@andybromberg.com">email me</a> — more posts will come in this series.</p>

<p>But before getting to a few FAQs, I want to wrap with perhaps my biggest takeaway from years of dealing with the media:</p>

<p><strong>It’s an exercise in <span class="highlighter">equanimity</span> and non-attachment to outcomes.</strong></p>

<p>The media is out of your control. No matter how much you try to make coverage perfect, it never will be.</p>

<p>There will be typos.</p>

<p>The title will be horrible.</p>

<p>You’ll be quoted out of context.</p>

<p>They’ll get some critical fact wrong.</p>

<p>Something off-the-record will get quoted.</p>

<p>The article will be delayed with no communication.</p>

<p>A surprise hit piece will land, filled with inaccuracies.</p>

<p>The writeup will be really short, even after you spent hours with the journalist.</p>

<p>They’ll take the story in a totally different direction than you wanted or expected.</p>

<p>They’ll feel a need to put “counterbalancing” negativity on an otherwise-positive story.</p>

<hr />

<p>Aaron Zamost, former head of comms at Square, wrote a piece ten years ago that I still think about: <a href="https://medium.com/backchannel/how-the-tech-press-forces-a-narrative-on-companies-it-covers-5f89fdb7793e">What’s Your Hour in ‘Silicon Valley Time’?</a>. Your company’s story will evolve outside of your control, and that article is the best encapsulation I’ve seen of the cycle.</p>

<p>You can work to minimize those issues, but at the end of the day — that’s life. It’ll happen, and it’s the cost of doing business for working with the media (see <a href="#a-note-on-going-direct">A note on “Going Direct”</a> above for an alternative — or complementary — path…).</p>

<p>I personally still think it’s worth it. And I’ve learned so much that can be generalized far beyond PR through working with the media.</p>

<p>But: it’s an exercise in equanimity and being unattached to any specific outcome.</p>

<p>Build great relationships, make your pitch, play the iterated game well, and let the chips fall where they may.</p>

<p>Good luck out there.</p>

<p><em>Part II will cover the tactics of how I’d execute a launch with PR.</em></p>

<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/rulebook-400-73ed2ef06.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/rulebook-600-73ed2ef06.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/rulebook-800-73ed2ef06.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/rulebook-1000-73ed2ef06.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/rulebook-400-40190185b.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/rulebook-600-40190185b.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/rulebook-800-40190185b.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/rulebook-1000-40190185b.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/startup-pr-rulebook/rulebook-800-40190185b.png" width="1881" height="485" /></picture>

<h2 id="other-faqs">Other FAQs</h2>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="can-i-read-articles-before-they-are-published">Can I read articles before they are published?</h3>

<p>No.</p>

<p>Absent unusual circumstances, you will not be allowed to see an article before a media outlet publishes it — you’ll read it at the same time as everyone else.</p>

<p>If you have a good relationship or an open line of communication with the journalist, you may be able to get them to answer some general questions about the direction they’re taking or what they’re focusing on, but it’s very unlikely you’ll be able to see any text itself.</p>

<p>One place you <em>may</em> be able to get <em>some</em> visibility is in the quotes. When you’re talking to a journalist, you can make requests about the quotes they will use. Two common ones:</p>
<ol>
  <li>I’d like to approve any quotes you attribute directly to me. Is that acceptable?</li>
  <li>Can you send me any quotes from this conversation you’re going to use so I can confirm you’re quoting me accurately?</li>
</ol>

<p>To be clear: they can (and often will) say “no” to those requests. But you can try!</p>

<p>On the former: there’s little upside to them saying “yes” unless talking to you is something they <em>really</em> want to do. If you have leverage, it’s worth trying.</p>

<p>On the latter: for obvious reasons, this only works if the conversation isn’t being recorded. And often, if you ask, they’ll just say <em>“oh let’s just record the conversation, that’ll make sure we get it accurately.”</em></p>

<p>You can imagine that <em>“confirm you’re quoting me accurately”</em> could be weaponized in the hands of a good PR firm or source to make sure that only approved quotes are put in, so journalists are hesitant to allow it.</p>

<p>The most common time a version of these requests are granted are if you are talking off-the-record or on background, but say to the journalist: <em>“I might be willing to put some of this on the record [or on background] — if there’s anything you want to use, let me know and I can approve a quote or give you a new one along the same lines if I’m comfortable.”</em></p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="are-the-conversations-recorded">Are the conversations recorded?</h3>

<p>Most on-the-record media conversations I have are recorded by the journalist. This allows them to make sure they don’t misquote you, and saves them from needing to scribble everything down. This is true of phone, video, and in-person conversations.</p>

<p>In general, journalists need to get your permission to do this. They’ll ask at the beginning of the conversation, <em>“are you okay if I record this?”</em></p>

<p>It doesn’t really make sense to deny that permission, because if you’re speaking on-the-record anyway, they could use whatever you say regardless — and presumably you’d rather them get it right.</p>

<p>Particularly if you’re going into a conversation you think might be contentious, you may <em>also</em> want to record it yourself! That way, if the journalist ends up misquoting you or taking something out of context, you have your own reference material.</p>

<p>The easiest way to do this is just a voice recording on your phone (or on your computer, if the call is happening on your phone). Make sure to ask permission. You can say something like <em>“is it okay if I record this? I may want to give it to my exec team for context so they know how I’ve been discussing the topic.”</em></p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="crisis--responsive-communications">Crisis / responsive communications</h3>

<p>This post has focused on launches, but PR is also about responding to crises, managing your brand, and generally trying to shape the news about your company.</p>

<p>I may do another post on crisis comms — it’s a whole separate art, far too much to cover in an FAQ — but for now, one principle worth mentioning:</p>

<p>You don’t always need to “correct the record,” and you <em>definitely</em> don’t always need to give a quote to the journalist writing a negative story.</p>

<p>Most founders have an impulse to talk to the journalist covering the story and try to explain things from their perspective. This <em>can</em> help, but often backfires. The reporter picks and chooses what to include, and often it’s not what you want.</p>

<p>News cycles move fast in today’s world, and the audience will move on from the story. Yes, it can be frustrating to have untrue things written about you without your rebuttal in the article, but it’s even worse to drag it out and make it a long-term distraction.</p>

<p>Again: great PR firms can be a huge help with this. They have seen many similar situations and can bring a level-headed perspective.</p>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="journalists-vs-editors">Journalists vs. editors</h3>

<p><strong>Journalists</strong> are on the ground, writing the stories. The role of <strong>editors</strong> varies publication to publication (and sometimes even <em>within</em> a publication).</p>

<p>Editors can be responsible for approving stories, assigning stories to reporters, editing their stories, and generally overseeing the newsroom. Sometimes they even write themselves.</p>

<p>For the sake of getting coverage, I’ve found it to be really helpful building relationships with both journalists and editors.</p>

<p>If you do well building a relationship with a journalist, they’ll lean on you as a source — which gives you an opportunity to provide value to them. Then they might advocate to their editor for a story you’re pitching them.</p>

<p>Editors, on the other hand, are great because they can assign your story to whoever is available or most appropriate. You’re not locked into a single journalist’s availability — you can be covered by whoever the editor thinks is best.</p>

<h2 class="no_toc" id="thank-yous">Thank yous</h2>

<p>Again: there is so much more that could be covered. If there’s anything you’re still wondering, please do <a href="mailto:andy@andybromberg.com">email me</a>.</p>

<p>A few people — plus a lot of direct experience — taught me everything I know about this topic.</p>

<p>At Sidewire, it was my co-founder Tucker Bounds. At CoinList, it was Blain Rethmeier, Trey Ditto, and the Ditto PR team. At Eco, Peter Hopkins, our Head of Comms, Content, and Education, as well as Trey and the Ditto team again. Thank you all!</p>

<hr class="end-of-article-divider" />

<h2 class="no_toc">Looking for more to read?</h2>

<nav class="post-navigation">
  <div class="prev-post">
    
    <a href="/investor-updates">
    
    <div class="post-nav-header"><i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-left post-nav-arrow"></i> Previous post</div>
    
    </a>
    
    
      <a href="/investor-updates">My investor update format</a>
    
  </div>
  <div class="next-post">
    <div class="post-nav-header">
        
        <a href="/fragrance-free">
        
        Next post <i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-right post-nav-arrow"></i>
        
        </a>
        
    </div>
    
      <a href="/fragrance-free">Try just one fragrance-free month</a>
    
  </div>
</nav>

<div>
    <p>Want to hear about new essays? Subscribe to my roughly-monthly <a href="https://andybromberg.substack.com">newsletter</a> recapping my recent writing and things I'm enjoying:</p>
    <div class="substack">
        <iframe src="https://andybromberg.substack.com/embed" width="480" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>
    </div>

    <p>And I'd love to hear from you directly: <a href="mailto:andy@andybromberg.com">andy@andybromberg.com</a></p>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What I wish I knew earlier in my career about the game of PR, working with journalists, and getting media coverage for your startup.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/startup-pr-rulebook.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/startup-pr-rulebook.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">My investor update format</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/investor-updates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My investor update format" /><published>2024-09-23T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-23T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/investor-updates</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/investor-updates"><![CDATA[<h2 id="context">Context</h2>

<p>This is the investor update format &amp; process I’ve developed over the last decade. I’m aware of at least 7 other startups that have copied it, and I hope to see many more!</p>

<p>Keeping up a regular — I prefer monthly — cadence of updates is great for several reasons:</p>
<ul>
  <li>it keeps you disciplined and accountable (and demonstrates that discipline)</li>
  <li>it puts you top-of-mind for your investors, generating unexpected opportunities</li>
  <li>it gives you a chance to ask investors for help, but in the context of providing valuable information to them</li>
  <li>it’s a chance to regularly reflect on your progress</li>
</ul>

<p>If all you want is to fulfill an obligation (real or perceived) to keep investors updated, you can do something shorter and less frequent. But if you want to keep them bought-in and invested in your success, a format like this will help.</p>

<p>Let’s get into the format, and then some specifics on how to execute it.</p>

<h2 id="format">Format</h2>

<!-- _includes/gmail_email.html -->

<div class="mac-window gmail-popup">
  <div class="mac-toolbar">
    <div class="mac-buttons">
      <span class="mac-button close"></span>
      <span class="mac-button minimize"></span>
      <span class="mac-button maximize"></span>
    </div>
    <div class="toolbar-title">Acme Corp. Investor Update [September 2024]</div>
  </div>
  <div class="gmail-email">
    <div class="email-header">
      
      <div class="email-subject">Acme Corp. Investor Update [September 2024]</div>
      
      <div class="email-metadata">
        
        <div class="email-field">
          <span class="field-label">From:</span>
          <div class="field-value">
            
              <img src="/assets/images/headshot.jpg" alt="Andy Bromberg" class="avatar andy-avatar" />
            
            <span class="name-email">
              <span class="name">Andy Bromberg</span>
              
              <span class="email">&lt;andy@andybromberg.com&gt;</span>
              
            </span>
          </div>
        </div>
        
        
        
        <div class="email-field">
          <span class="field-label">Date:</span>
          <span class="field-value">Sat, Oct 5, 7:35 AM</span>
        </div>
        
      </div>
    </div>
    <div class="email-divider"></div>
    <div class="email-body">
      <p><strong>This information is exclusively for Acme stakeholders. Please keep it confidential.</strong></p>

<p>Hi everyone — here’s your latest monthly update from Acme Corp. headquarters.</p>

<p><strong>tl;dr: September set a new record for contracted revenue - $[x]!; but we churned our third-biggest customer after an issue with downtime; we have made reliability our top Q4 product priority</strong></p>

<p><em>In the tl;dr: ideally at least one win and one challenge; no more than 4 items. Make sure to explain these further in the appropriate sections.</em></p>

<p><strong>Acme is:</strong> [blurb about Acme]</p>

<p><em>This blurb is useful both for existing investors to stay current on how you describe the business, and for anyone the email is forwarded to (more on that below).</em></p>

<p><strong>Asks</strong></p>

<p>1. [Request #1]</p>

<p>2. [Request #2]</p>

<p><em>Make asks extremely specific and easy to take action on — e.g. instead of ‘we want to talk to any consumer brands over $5MM in revenue,’ say ‘we’re looking for intros to [list of 5 brands], or any others like them over $5MM in revenue. Reply to this email if you know someone and I will send you a blurb to forward.’ Also: do not make them click anything. Nobody clicks out to external links in these emails.</em></p>

<p><strong>Acme Love</strong></p>

<p>[A couple highlights from customers or team, or other cool things that have happened. Images are great here.]</p>

<p><strong>Metrics</strong></p>

<p>[Charts of your key metrics, plus any brief commentary that would help explain them.]</p>

<p><strong>Product update</strong></p>

<p>What we worked on since last update:</p>

<p>- [bullets of what’s been shipped]</p>

<p>What’s up next:</p>

<p>- [bullets of what’s getting built]</p>

<p><strong>[Other]</strong></p>

<p><em>For some companies, this should be a section similar to ‘Product update’ but for sales, or marketing, or community — or anything else you think deserves a section. Every business is different.</em></p>

<p><strong>Team</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/">Jane Smith</a> joined as a Staff Software Engineer, Backend. She joins us from High Voltage Engineering Corporation where she led the team responsible for their particle accelerator monitoring systems.</p>

<p><strong>Thank yous</strong></p>

<p><strong>Georges Doriot</strong> at <strong>ARDC</strong> for a great introduction to leadership at Digital Equipment Corporation, a potential customer.</p>

<p><em>Keep a running list during the month of any investors that helped out. This list pays massive dividends — people really appreciate being recognized in front of their peers.</em></p>

<p><em>Often, when investors help out — especially on an item from the ‘Asks’ section — they say ‘hope this lands me on the list next month!’ If that’s not evidence that this works, I don’t know what is…</em></p>

<p><strong>In closing</strong></p>

<p>As ever, thank you for supporting Acme. I’m always available if you want to catch up. You can email me or reach me on iMessage/Signal/WhatsApp at [my number].</p>

<p>Andy</p>

    </div>
  </div>
</div>

<h2 id="process">Process</h2>

<h3 id="timing">Timing</h3>

<p>I recommend sending these on the same day every month — I send them on the 5th of the month (so the “September 2024” update comes on October 5th, 2024).</p>

<p>It’s useful to give yourself those couple days after the close of the month to write this up, but I am strict about including only things that happened <em>in the month of September.</em> Why?</p>

<p>Because if you include anything from the first 5 days of October, you’re mortgaging against your October update! And if you start including the first 5 days of the following month every time, then you’re losing the benefit of having a couple days “after close” to put the update together.</p>

<p>Being incredibly consistent — sending on the same day, every month, no matter what (weekends &amp; holidays included!) — costs you very little, but enforces real discipline on you and shows that discipline to investors (and they love it). It sets a drumbeat and keeps you accountable to making forward progress every month.</p>

<h3 id="sending">Sending</h3>

<p>I use <a href="https://mailsuite.com/en/">Mailsuite</a> (formerly Mailtrack). All the investors are in a Mailsuite “list,” and I create a “campaign” to that set of investors and hit send. This gives me open tracking (if someone “opens” it 100 times… it probably means they forwarded it around) and click tracking.</p>

<p>After I send to investors, I also forward it to the team. The content in the update shouldn’t be news to them, but it’s still nice for everyone to be able to see what we’re saying to investors each month.</p>

<h3 id="writing-process">Writing process</h3>

<p>The update looks long (and impressive) — but it really should only take a couple hours, at least in a normal month. Taking a few hours a month for the chance to communicate with my most invested supporters is a trade I’ll take all day. It keeps me accountable, keeps them informed, and keeps the company top-of-mind for them.</p>

<p>Depending on your team composition, other people can generally do the first drafts of at least:</p>
<ul>
  <li>metrics</li>
  <li>product update</li>
  <li>team</li>
</ul>

<p>That leaves you with:</p>
<ul>
  <li>tl;dr / summary — a useful exercise for the CEO to do every month!</li>
  <li>asks — you can crowdsource these as well, but you’re likely to have the best view</li>
  <li>Acme Love — other people can do this, but I find it fun (and it keeps you close to the customer and the team)</li>
  <li>thank yous — you were likely the recipient of the help, so you’re the one who would know</li>
  <li>and editing/polishing the whole thing</li>
</ul>

<p>Again: I’ve found this takes me (and friends who have copied this format) a couple hours. Well worth it!</p>

<h3 id="special-editions">Special editions</h3>

<p>Sometimes, a “special edition” is warranted — maybe you had a big launch or other news, or are changing strategy, or something else.</p>

<p>In these cases, I tend to remove a few sections from the typical update, and instead put a big “Update” section below the tl;dr and asks. There’s no need to be too rigid about the format — feel free to mix it up when called for.</p>

<h3 id="prose--reflections">Prose &amp; reflections</h3>

<p>Most of this update format is objective and bulleted. But if you have broad thoughts on your strategy, the market, or anything else that might be relevant, you should absolutely include them (perhaps in their own section).</p>

<p>I’ve gotten the best feedback on updates where I included some meaningful thoughts. Some investors don’t love it (“just give me the numbers!”), but most find it helpful and interesting. You’ll never please everyone.</p>

<h3 id="intentional-forwarding">Intentional forwarding</h3>

<p>Aside from the accountability, getting help, and staying top-of-mind, one of the best uses of a well-written investor update is having it be intentionally forwarded.</p>

<p>Say you’re looking for an introduction to a potential new investor (or candidate, or partner…). When someone volunteers to set up the intro, just have them forward your most recent update with some commentary.</p>

<!-- _includes/gmail_email.html -->

<div class="mac-window gmail-popup">
  <div class="mac-toolbar">
    <div class="mac-buttons">
      <span class="mac-button close"></span>
      <span class="mac-button minimize"></span>
      <span class="mac-button maximize"></span>
    </div>
    <div class="toolbar-title">FW: Acme Corp. Investor Update [September 2024]</div>
  </div>
  <div class="gmail-email">
    <div class="email-header">
      
      <div class="email-subject">FW: Acme Corp. Investor Update [September 2024]</div>
      
      <div class="email-metadata">
        
        <div class="email-field">
          <span class="field-label">From:</span>
          <div class="field-value">
            
              <span class="avatar" style="background-color: #FF7043">G</span>
            
            <span class="name-email">
              <span class="name">Georges Doriot</span>
              
              <span class="email">&lt;georges@ardc.com&gt;</span>
              
            </span>
          </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div class="email-field">
          <span class="field-label">To:</span>
          <div class="field-value">
            
              <span class="avatar" style="background-color: #4285F4">J</span>
            
            <span class="name-email">
              <span class="name">John Hay Whitney</span>
              
              <span class="email">&lt;jhw@whitney.com&gt;</span>
              
            </span>
          </div>
        </div>
        
        
        <div class="email-field">
          <span class="field-label">Date:</span>
          <span class="field-value">Sun, Oct 6, 1:07 PM</span>
        </div>
        
      </div>
    </div>
    <div class="email-divider"></div>
    <div class="email-body">
      <p>JH — I’m an investor in Acme, and they’re gearing up for their next round. The CEO, Andy, was interested in meeting you. Below is their most recent investor update, for context. Let me know if you’d like to connect.</p>

<p>- Georges</p>

<p><em>Begin forwarded message:</em></p>

<p><strong>From:</strong> ‘Andy Bromberg’ &lt;andy@andybromberg.com&gt;</p>

<p><strong>Subject: Acme Corp. Investor Update [September 2024]</strong></p>

<p>…</p>

    </div>
  </div>
</div>

<p>This brings the recipient into the fold, gives them context, shows them your willingness to honestly share both wins and challenges with stakeholders, and — if you’ve written it well and the company is doing well! — demonstrates competency and progress.</p>

<p>I’ve found it far more effective than a vanilla email with a brief blurb.</p>

<h3 id="confidentiality">Confidentiality</h3>

<p>In line with the above… you also need to assume that everything in your updates will get forwarded to competition, other investors, and more (or could end up in the news!).</p>

<p>So write it with that in mind. Sometimes investors will say you should include even more in your updates, and/or more sensitive information. It’s fine to say “happy to chat about that live or answer any questions directly — I’m just sensitive to blasting that out with the potential of it being forwarded.”</p>

<p>(Or you can include more — everyone has different preferences.)</p>

<hr class="end-of-article-divider" />

<h2 class="no_toc">Looking for more to read?</h2>

<nav class="post-navigation">
  <div class="prev-post">
    
    <a href="/toxic-progress-paradox">
    
    <div class="post-nav-header"><i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-left post-nav-arrow"></i> Previous post</div>
    
    </a>
    
    
      <a href="/toxic-progress-paradox">The Toxic Progress Paradox</a>
    
  </div>
  <div class="next-post">
    <div class="post-nav-header">
        
        <a href="/startup-pr-rulebook">
        
        Next post <i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-right post-nav-arrow"></i>
        
        </a>
        
    </div>
    
      <a href="/startup-pr-rulebook">Startup PR, Part I: the rules of the game</a>
    
  </div>
</nav>

<div>
    <p>Want to hear about new essays? Subscribe to my roughly-monthly <a href="https://andybromberg.substack.com">newsletter</a> recapping my recent writing and things I'm enjoying:</p>
    <div class="substack">
        <iframe src="https://andybromberg.substack.com/embed" width="480" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>
    </div>

    <p>And I'd love to hear from you directly: <a href="mailto:andy@andybromberg.com">andy@andybromberg.com</a></p>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Here's the investor update format & process I've developed over the last decade.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/investor-updates.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/investor-updates.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Toxic Progress Paradox</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/toxic-progress-paradox" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Toxic Progress Paradox" /><published>2024-09-09T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-09T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/toxic-progress-paradox</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/toxic-progress-paradox"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Progress is Good.</strong> (but sometimes toxic — more on that in a moment.)</p>

<p>In the last hundred years, we’ve invented the internet, nuclear power, DNA sequencing, the laser, GPS, MRIs, integrated circuits, plus compounds and materials like Pencillin, Metformin, graphene, Kevlar, Inconel, aerogels, and reinforced carbon-carbon that have unlocked tremendous advances in medicine and technology.</p>

<p>These inventions and discoveries power the engine of progress. And, broadly, since the pace of progress began accelerating with the industrial revolution, global standards of living have soared.<label for="sn-1" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-1" class="margin-toggle" /><span class="sidenote">See the <a href="https://humanprogress.org/datasets/">Human Progress datasets</a> from the Cato Institute, or <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/">Our World in Data</a>.</span></p>

<p>Just how much are we inventing?</p>

<p>Look at this hockey stick graph of how many patents have been awarded each year in the US:</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/patents-400-b7f9f3abd.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/patents-600-b7f9f3abd.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/patents-800-b7f9f3abd.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/patents-1000-b7f9f3abd.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/patents-400-05b6b39ee.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/patents-600-05b6b39ee.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/patents-800-05b6b39ee.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/patents-1000-05b6b39ee.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/patents-800-05b6b39ee.png" width="2032" height="1290" /></picture>

<p>Or check out the <a href="https://www.cas.org/cas-data/cas-registry">Chemical Abstracts Service Registry</a>, which logs all chemical compounds created or identified (another hockey stick!):</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/cas-400-3c46991d3.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/cas-600-3c46991d3.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/cas-800-3c46991d3.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/cas-1000-3c46991d3.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/cas-400-b478909e7.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/cas-600-b478909e7.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/cas-800-b478909e7.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/cas-1000-b478909e7.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/cas-800-b478909e7.png" width="1626" height="998" /></picture>

<p>We’re making progress! Every year, we create new and wonderful things.</p>

<p>But: we also get things wrong sometimes along the way. (And we usually don’t find out for awhile.)</p>

<p>For example: asbestos was the best answer we’d ever found for fireproofing buildings.</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/asbestos-400-751824509.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/asbestos-600-751824509.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/asbestos-800-751824509.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/asbestos-1000-751824509.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/asbestos-400-60a17e4fc.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/asbestos-600-60a17e4fc.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/asbestos-800-60a17e4fc.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/asbestos-1000-60a17e4fc.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/asbestos-800-60a17e4fc.png" width="1800" height="600" /></picture>

<p>But it turned out to cause mesothelioma, a deadly cancer.</p>

<hr />

<p>Leaded gas was more efficient than any vehicle fuel we’d developed.</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/leaded_gas-400-5a09c52f3.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/leaded_gas-600-5a09c52f3.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/leaded_gas-800-5a09c52f3.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/leaded_gas-1000-5a09c52f3.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/leaded_gas-400-c140c62dd.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/leaded_gas-600-c140c62dd.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/leaded_gas-800-c140c62dd.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/leaded_gas-1000-c140c62dd.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/leaded_gas-800-c140c62dd.png" width="1800" height="600" /></picture>

<p>But it crippled cognitive development in children.</p>

<hr />

<p>BPA — Bisphenol A — is exceptional for making useful plastic products.</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/bpa-400-8539107e0.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/bpa-600-8539107e0.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/bpa-800-8539107e0.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/bpa-1000-8539107e0.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/bpa-400-05d5a47eb.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/bpa-600-05d5a47eb.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/bpa-800-05d5a47eb.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/bpa-1000-05d5a47eb.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/bpa-800-05d5a47eb.png" width="1800" height="600" /></picture>

<p>But it turned out to be an endocrine disrupter, creating negative impacts of which we are still understanding the magnitude.</p>

<hr />

<p>Hexachlorophene was a great antibacterial and disinfectant.</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/hexachlorophene-400-661ab19a7.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/hexachlorophene-600-661ab19a7.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/hexachlorophene-800-661ab19a7.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/hexachlorophene-1000-661ab19a7.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/hexachlorophene-400-6f687e5cb.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/hexachlorophene-600-6f687e5cb.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/hexachlorophene-800-6f687e5cb.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/hexachlorophene-1000-6f687e5cb.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/hexachlorophene-800-6f687e5cb.png" width="1800" height="600" /></picture>

<p>But it killed children and caused brain damage before being pulled off the market.</p>

<hr />

<p>Thalidomide was a miracle drug for morning sickness.</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/thalidomide-400-1e666bbde.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/thalidomide-600-1e666bbde.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/thalidomide-800-1e666bbde.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/thalidomide-1000-1e666bbde.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/thalidomide-400-f52691227.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/thalidomide-600-f52691227.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/thalidomide-800-f52691227.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/thalidomide-1000-f52691227.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/toxic-progress-paradox/thalidomide-800-f52691227.png" width="1800" height="600" /></picture>

<p>But it caused birth defects and death in children whose mothers took it.</p>

<hr />

<p>Technology is a double-edged sword — just about anything with new capabilities can be good or evil.</p>

<p>But sometimes one edge is sharper than the other.</p>

<p>In some cases the winning side is clear cut (internet: good; Thalidomide: bad). But sometimes it’s less obvious (DDT?).</p>

<p>And in many cases, we don’t find out about the problems until much later (BPA).</p>

<hr />

<p>Here’s the root of the Toxic Progress Paradox:</p>

<p><strong>Some percentage of new compounds and technologies will turn out to be bad, and as the pace of progress accelerates, so too will the raw number of bad outcomes from that progress.</strong></p>

<p>Said another way: if we commercialize 10,000 new compounds or technologies in a year, we’re much more likely to create some bad outcomes than if we only brought 100 to market. And we are indeed creating more every year, so along with all the benefits that brings, we’re also very likely increasing negative impacts.</p>

<p>The Toxic Progress Paradox itself:</p>

<p><strong>For the long-term benefit of humanity, we want the fastest progress possible; but, along the way, we also want as few bad outcomes as possible.</strong></p>

<p>Does that mean we should stop developing new things? Or “pause” until we can get that error rate to zero? No!</p>

<hr />

<p>So what <em>do</em> we do? How do we cut the knot of the paradox?</p>

<p><strong>Most important: on a individual level, we need to take personal responsibility for our own decisions. We shouldn’t assume that “it’s all fine” — history shows us that it often isn’t.</strong></p>

<p><strong>That means being intentional about when we embrace new exposures of any type — technological, chemical, or otherwise. We should make our own individual tradeoffs based on our risk appetite, how much the new thing benefits us, and the information available to us.</strong></p>

<p>Sometimes this is easy, sometimes it’s hard. But it’s worthwhile.</p>

<hr />

<p>When I talk about this Toxic Progress Paradox, most people immediately jump to the big-picture view: that we should (of course) be seeking to minimize the “error rate” of new technology.</p>

<p>They jump right into (reasonable!) debate about the best mechanisms to accomplish this. Is the answer market mechanisms, holding people and companies responsible — and liable — when they create one of those errors?<label for="sn-2" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-2" class="margin-toggle" /><span class="sidenote">Cue Munger: “Show me the incentive and I’ll show you the outcome” (although does anyone have a citation for that quote?).</span> Is it regulatory agencies? Something else?</p>

<p>They begin to ask: how much progress — if any — should we be willing to sacrifice to minimize that error rate? How free should the markets be? How constrained or unconstrained should the regulatory environment be?</p>

<p>And while those questions are undoubtedly important (and ones on which I have an opinion as well), I don’t think they are the right place to go first. I believe the most important takeaway from this paradox is the individual one, outlined above:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We need to take personal responsibility for our own decisions. We shouldn’t assume that “it’s all fine” — history shows us that it often isn’t.</p>

  <p>That means being intentional about when we embrace new exposures of any type — technological, chemical, or otherwise. We should make our own individual tradeoffs based on our risk appetite, how much the new thing benefits us, and the information available to us.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s easy to get caught up in outrage about how things work in the world (and how they don’t). But if you spend all your time thinking about how to solve that problem, you’ll miss the one right in front of you: your own life.</p>

<p>Beware the Toxic Progress Paradox, and — as you’ve heard before — put your oxygen mask on before assisting others.</p>

<hr class="end-of-article-divider" />

<h2 class="no_toc">Looking for more to read?</h2>

<nav class="post-navigation">
  <div class="prev-post">
    
    <a href="/freedom-phones">
    
    <div class="post-nav-header"><i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-left post-nav-arrow"></i> Previous post</div>
    
    </a>
    
    
      <a href="/freedom-phones">Freedom Phones and Focus Accounts</a>
    
  </div>
  <div class="next-post">
    <div class="post-nav-header">
        
        <a href="/investor-updates">
        
        Next post <i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-right post-nav-arrow"></i>
        
        </a>
        
    </div>
    
      <a href="/investor-updates">My investor update format</a>
    
  </div>
</nav>

<div>
    <p>Want to hear about new essays? Subscribe to my roughly-monthly <a href="https://andybromberg.substack.com">newsletter</a> recapping my recent writing and things I'm enjoying:</p>
    <div class="substack">
        <iframe src="https://andybromberg.substack.com/embed" width="480" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>
    </div>

    <p>And I'd love to hear from you directly: <a href="mailto:andy@andybromberg.com">andy@andybromberg.com</a></p>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Progress is Good, but we get things wrong sometimes. What should we do in such a world?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/toxic-progress-paradox.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/toxic-progress-paradox.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Freedom Phones and Focus Accounts</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/freedom-phones" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Freedom Phones and Focus Accounts" /><published>2024-09-08T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-08T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/freedom-phones</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/freedom-phones"><![CDATA[<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/phone-on-desk-400-172b35e68.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/phone-on-desk-600-172b35e68.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/phone-on-desk-800-172b35e68.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/phone-on-desk-1000-172b35e68.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/phone-on-desk-400-a8ead85e7.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/phone-on-desk-600-a8ead85e7.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/phone-on-desk-800-a8ead85e7.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/phone-on-desk-1000-a8ead85e7.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/phone-on-desk-800-a8ead85e7.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<p>Inspired by <a href="https://medium.com/@swaaanson/my-2021-life-experiments-d56f51039f2b">Jon Swanson</a>, this is one of the greatest quality-of-life improvements I’ve made in recent memory.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-wanted">What I wanted</h2>

<p>A second phone — the Freedom Phone — with:</p>
<ul>
  <li>only approved “utility” apps that would not distract me</li>
  <li>sufficient capabilities that I could spend a week abroad without my (normal) Matrix Phone</li>
  <li>the ability to receive emergency phone calls from family
    <ul>
      <li>but them not needing to remember/try a second phone number for me</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>nobody other than family in my contacts</li>
</ul>

<p>The Freedom Phone is my default phone, and I feel so much better for it.</p>

<h2 id="my-freedom-phone-setup">My Freedom Phone setup</h2>

<p>I ended up with a Google Pixel 8 (I wanted to try the “other” ecosystem after my last Android more than a decade ago…) on Google Fi. On it, I took the following steps:</p>

<h3 id="install-only-the-following-apps">Install only the following apps</h3>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Transport</strong></td>
      <td>Google Maps, Uber</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Content</strong></td>
      <td>Spotify</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Utilities</strong></td>
      <td>Phone, Camera, Authenticator, Calendar</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Thinking</strong></td>
      <td>ChatGPT, Google Keep for notes (soon to be replaced by Obsidian mobile)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Other</strong></td>
      <td>Home security apps</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>So far, I’ve been happy with ChatGPT on there — I enjoy being able to look things up without the potential of getting distracted by the internet, and I haven’t overused it. I’ll keep checking in on this, though, and if I feel I’m defeating the purpose of the phone, I’ll take it off.</p>

<p>I feel similarly about Spotify, Soundcloud, and Reader — I sometimes like to listen while on walks, or read when I have downtime. But if I felt myself getting pulled towards content I didn’t want to be default consuming, I’d yank them off.</p>

<p>I also installed a minimal Android launcher called <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=app.olauncher&amp;hl=en_US&amp;pli=1">OLauncher</a> — so my home screen looks like this:</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/homescreen-400-700cbd3cb.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/homescreen-600-700cbd3cb.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/homescreen-800-700cbd3cb.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/homescreen-1000-700cbd3cb.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/homescreen-400-49d2eb83d.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/homescreen-600-49d2eb83d.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/homescreen-800-49d2eb83d.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/homescreen-1000-49d2eb83d.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/homescreen-800-49d2eb83d.png" width="10688" height="6012" /></picture>

<h3 id="uninstall-or-disable-everything-else">Uninstall or disable everything else</h3>

<p>I don’t even want the option of getting on the internet. So I disabled access to Chrome, Gmail, and most everything else by going to Settings → Apps → See all apps → Chrome/Gmail/whatever → Disable</p>

<p>I also uninstalled every app I could, and turned off all notifications other than phone calls or security app alerts.</p>

<h3 id="set-up-emergency-contacts--conditional-call-forwarding">Set up emergency contacts &amp; “conditional call forwarding”</h3>

<p>I put my wife and our families in the Freedom Phone’s contacts, plus my doctor and our home security system — and nobody else. If I need to reach them, I can.</p>

<p>But they may also need to reach <em>me</em>, and I don’t want them to have to try two numbers in case of emergency.</p>

<p>So I’ve set up what Verizon (my primary carrier) calls “<a href="https://www.verizon.com/support/knowledge-base-181139/">conditional call forwarding</a>” from my normal phone to the Freedom Phone. When someone calls my primary number, it rings all the way through and then, if I don’t answer, it starts ringing the Freedom Phone.</p>

<p>I <em>wish</em> Verizon let me do that selectively (i.e. only conditionally forward my family’s calls), but they don’t. So every call I get on my Matrix Phone ends up ringing through to the Freedom Phone. But since I don’t have anyone in my contacts, I have no idea who it is, and I happily ignore unless they call me multiple times in a row.</p>

<p>Then, the final part of the setup is to put my primary phone on Do Not Disturb when I have my Freedom Phone. That way, incoming calls instantly get bounced to the Freedom Phone instead of ringing through on the primary before shifting over.</p>

<p>In summary:<label for="mn-1" class="margin-toggle">⊕</label>
<input type="checkbox" id="mn-1" class="margin-toggle" />
<span class="marginnote">
With this setup, if they <em>text</em> my normal number, I won’t see it until I get back to my computer or the other device. And that’s fine with me — if they really need me, they’ll call.
</span></p>
<ul>
  <li>put emergency contacts in Freedom Phone</li>
  <li>set up “conditional call forwarding” from primary phone to Freedom Phone</li>
  <li>put Matrix Phone on DND when I have the Freedom Phone</li>
</ul>

<picture loading="lazy" class="article-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/iphone-400-616171697.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/iphone-600-616171697.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/iphone-800-616171697.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/iphone-1000-616171697.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/iphone-400-11e26dc58.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/iphone-600-11e26dc58.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/iphone-800-11e26dc58.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/iphone-1000-11e26dc58.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/iphone-800-11e26dc58.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<h3 id="security">Security</h3>

<p>A security note: if you aren’t already a full-on security nut with an entirely separate, otherwise-unused phone number for critical/high-value services (mitigating SIM swap risk), it’s not a bad idea to link those services to the Freedom Phone instead. It’s better than your normal phone number, which lots more people know is yours, and thus is a more obvious attack vector.</p>

<p>(And of course, you shouldn’t be using SMS 2FA anyway — but companies can fall victim to social engineering by attackers with access to phone numbers even if non-SMS MFA is enabled, so it’s best to give sensitive services the most secure phone number you can.)</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="focus-account">Focus Account</h2>

<p>After loving the Freedom Phone experience, I wanted the same on my computer. So I set up a separate user account called Focus.</p>

<p>Here’s the setup for the Focus user account:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Install the app <a href="https://heyfocus.com/">Focus</a>, include every site I find distracting, and set it on a maximum-length focus block (so those sites are always blocked when I’m in that account)</li>
  <li>Only open the apps and sites I need when focusing (for me, usually: Obsidian, VSCode/Cursor, sometimes email, ChatGPT/Claude)</li>
</ul>

<p>And then quit / close everything else — no messengers!</p>

<p>I went into system settings and turned on Fast User Switching, and now I can easily swap from the menu bar to my Focus account.</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/fast-user-switching-400-6e25ff011.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/fast-user-switching-600-6e25ff011.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/fast-user-switching-800-6e25ff011.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/fast-user-switching-1000-6e25ff011.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/fast-user-switching-400-ad9c554a6.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/fast-user-switching-600-ad9c554a6.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/fast-user-switching-800-ad9c554a6.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/fast-user-switching-1000-ad9c554a6.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/freedom-phones/fast-user-switching-800-ad9c554a6.png" width="2558" height="1438" /></picture>

<p>Now, whenever I want to work, I switch over to it, and can stay dialed in. I’ve found the friction of changing user accounts (and entering my password) is high enough to prevent me from mindlessly swapping over to the main account.</p>

<h2 id="why">Why?</h2>

<p>I find the internet hard to resist. It’s an incredible place — but I also know that I feel better when I’m intentional about what I’m consuming and when I’m consuming it. And, personally, I find it challenging to actively manage that consumption.</p>

<p>The best solution I’ve found is “sensible defaults” like the Freedom Phone and Focus Account, which add friction to mindless consumption.</p>

<hr />

<p>Taking time off-the-grid reminds me of the dangers of the internet. When I’m disconnected, I feel great. And when I come back online, I can sense my immediacy and presence slipping away as I plug back into chat apps and the internet and everything that comes with it.</p>

<p>I’ve found intentional use of a Freedom Phone and Focus Account to be happy middle grounds. They don’t require my becoming a luddite — I still love the internet, and love being instantly connected to my friends and family. But I just don’t need those every second of every day, and it’s easier for me to find that balance through a system like this than through force of will.</p>

<hr class="end-of-article-divider" />

<h2 class="no_toc">Looking for more to read?</h2>

<nav class="post-navigation">
  <div class="prev-post">
    
    <a href="/minimum-effective-quantification">
    
    <div class="post-nav-header"><i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-left post-nav-arrow"></i> Previous post</div>
    
    </a>
    
    
      <a href="/minimum-effective-quantification">Minimum Effective Quantification</a>
    
  </div>
  <div class="next-post">
    <div class="post-nav-header">
        
        <a href="/toxic-progress-paradox">
        
        Next post <i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-right post-nav-arrow"></i>
        
        </a>
        
    </div>
    
      <a href="/toxic-progress-paradox">The Toxic Progress Paradox</a>
    
  </div>
</nav>

<div>
    <p>Want to hear about new essays? Subscribe to my roughly-monthly <a href="https://andybromberg.substack.com">newsletter</a> recapping my recent writing and things I'm enjoying:</p>
    <div class="substack">
        <iframe src="https://andybromberg.substack.com/embed" width="480" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>
    </div>

    <p>And I'd love to hear from you directly: <a href="mailto:andy@andybromberg.com">andy@andybromberg.com</a></p>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to unplug from the matrix, at least a little bit.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/freedom-phones.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/freedom-phones.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Minimum Effective Quantification</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/minimum-effective-quantification" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Minimum Effective Quantification" /><published>2024-09-04T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-04T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/minimum-effective-quantification</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/minimum-effective-quantification"><![CDATA[<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/notebook-desk-400-58f1f360e.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/notebook-desk-600-58f1f360e.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/notebook-desk-800-58f1f360e.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/notebook-desk-1000-58f1f360e.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/notebook-desk-400-0acad7c88.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/notebook-desk-600-0acad7c88.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/notebook-desk-800-0acad7c88.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/notebook-desk-1000-0acad7c88.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/notebook-desk-800-0acad7c88.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<p>I used to be an extreme <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantified_self">Quantified Self</a> adherent. I pricked my finger daily to measure glucose and ketones, tracked every meal and workout, logged every alcoholic drink and supplement, and much more.</p>

<picture loading="lazy"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/spreadsheet-400-a5645331d.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/spreadsheet-600-a5645331d.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/spreadsheet-800-a5645331d.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/spreadsheet-1000-a5645331d.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/spreadsheet-400-b385eb32a.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/spreadsheet-600-b385eb32a.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/spreadsheet-800-b385eb32a.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/spreadsheet-1000-b385eb32a.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/minimum-effective-quantification/spreadsheet-800-b385eb32a.png" width="1944" height="76" /></picture>

<p><label for="mn-1" class="margin-toggle">⊕</label>
<input type="checkbox" id="mn-1" class="margin-toggle" />
<span class="marginnote">
(not even all the tabs of that spreadsheet…)</span></p>

<p>It was useful at times, and I empirically learned a lot about my body — alcohol wrecks my sleep; a stint on keto dramatically improved my body composition; rice and sweet potatoes don’t spike my blood glucose; I respond better to heavy lifting….</p>

<p>But I reached a point of diminishing returns (and still sometimes wonder if the returns were ever that good in the first place). I broadly understood what made me feel good and what didn’t, and the effort of tracking so many parameters no longer felt worthwhile.</p>

<p>I threw it all away, and tracked nothing. But that didn’t feel right either.</p>

<p>So I found a new path. Instead of bottoms-up measuring <em>everything</em> and trying to find insights in the data, I went top-down and asked myself:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On a day where I feel great, what 2-5 quantitative measures are likely to be true?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The answer to that question — your Minimum Effective Quantification (MEQ) — will be different for everyone. Here are mine:</p>
<ul>
  <li>I slept 8 hours the night before</li>
  <li>I walked at least 12,000 steps</li>
  <li>I did at least 100 pushups in scattered sets of 10 throughout the day (i.e. not part of a concentrated workout)</li>
  <li>I did at least 4 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique">pomodoros</a> (25 minutes each) of deep, uninterrupted work</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>If those four criteria (my Minimum Effective Quantification) are true, it’s very likely I feel <em>great</em> at the end of the day.</strong></p>

<p>Now, I simply measure those four each day. I write them down in my notebook — tallying pomodoros and sets of 10 pushups, looking at my pedometer at the end of the day, and logging sleep duration.</p>

<p>Then, each week, I write down how many days I hit the bar, and the totals: how many weekly steps, pushups, pomodoros…</p>

<p>I’m motivated to set absolute weekly numerical records, but more importantly, I try to get all four to 7/7 days each week. At the end of the day, if I’m at 10k steps, I go and walk around. If I’m at 80 pushups, I close out the last 20.</p>

<p>And as a result, I feel really, really good.</p>

<p>What’s your MEQ? Is it 60 minutes of yoga? Less than 2500 calories? An hour talking to friends or family?</p>

<p>Try answering the MEQ question for yourself and log your results for a couple weeks — adding an evening question of “how good did I feel today?” I bet you’ll like it.</p>

<hr />

<p>A caveat: of course, quantification has multiple purposes:</p>
<ul>
  <li>feeling good daily</li>
  <li>measuring experiments</li>
  <li>improving/tracking health or performance long-term</li>
</ul>

<p>The MEQ process is great for feeling good daily. But it doesn’t serve the others.</p>

<p>For the experiments: if I’m changing my diet, I might track my meals. If I’m adjusting my exercise routine, I’ll keep a closer eye on body composition. If I’m taking a new supplement, I’ll measure the relevant markers or outcomes.</p>

<p>For the long-term impacts, I still get regular blood and other biomarker tests and track my progress.</p>

<p>But all of that is low-lift or only occasional. The MEQ process is about getting the most out of a simple daily ritual, and making sure you feel great every day.</p>

<hr class="end-of-article-divider" />

<h2 class="no_toc">Looking for more to read?</h2>

<nav class="post-navigation">
  <div class="prev-post">
    
    <a href="/useful-reference-calls">
    
    <div class="post-nav-header"><i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-left post-nav-arrow"></i> Previous post</div>
    
    </a>
    
    
      <a href="/useful-reference-calls">Tools for getting the truth on reference calls</a>
    
  </div>
  <div class="next-post">
    <div class="post-nav-header">
        
        <a href="/freedom-phones">
        
        Next post <i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-right post-nav-arrow"></i>
        
        </a>
        
    </div>
    
      <a href="/freedom-phones">Freedom Phones and Focus Accounts</a>
    
  </div>
</nav>

<div>
    <p>Want to hear about new essays? Subscribe to my roughly-monthly <a href="https://andybromberg.substack.com">newsletter</a> recapping my recent writing and things I'm enjoying:</p>
    <div class="substack">
        <iframe src="https://andybromberg.substack.com/embed" width="480" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>
    </div>

    <p>And I'd love to hear from you directly: <a href="mailto:andy@andybromberg.com">andy@andybromberg.com</a></p>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to get the most out of quantifying your life, without the overhead.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/minimum-effective-quantification.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/minimum-effective-quantification.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tools for getting the truth on reference calls</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/useful-reference-calls" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tools for getting the truth on reference calls" /><published>2024-08-22T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/useful-reference-calls</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/useful-reference-calls"><![CDATA[<h2 id="background">Background</h2>

<p>Reference calls are tough. Most often, by the time you do them, you’re pretty sure the candidate is a good fit for the role. You’re looking for novel evidence — anything that would make you second-guess the decision to hire them, or that would change how you think about their responsibilities.</p>

<p>But that purpose runs counter to pretty much everyone’s desire to not speak ill of others.</p>

<p>Whether the reference was given to you by the candidate or it’s a backchannel, the person on the other end of the line tends to be positive. That default positivity leaves you reading the tea leaves and making often-flawed inferential leaps from their tone of voice or the way they answered the question.</p>

<p>So this all boils down to: how can you get the <em>negative or constructive parts of the truth</em> about a candidate?</p>

<p>Here are the two tools I’ve been happiest with:</p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>Granting implicit permission for honesty</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Forced quantitative questions</strong></li>
</ol>

<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/two-person-call-400-366c64aa8.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/two-person-call-600-366c64aa8.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/two-person-call-800-366c64aa8.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/two-person-call-1000-366c64aa8.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/two-person-call-400-61d96ef90.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/two-person-call-600-61d96ef90.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/two-person-call-800-61d96ef90.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/two-person-call-1000-61d96ef90.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/two-person-call-800-61d96ef90.png" width="1904" height="640" /></picture>

<h2 id="tool-1-granting-implicit-permission-for-honesty">Tool #1: granting implicit permission for honesty</h2>

<p>This requires you having interviewed the candidate — we’ll call them Carlos — earlier in the process and pulled out specific challenging situations or feedback from <em>him</em> that you can then reference. Good questions for this include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>what was the feedback you got most often when you were working at that job?</li>
  <li>tell me about a time when you had a conflict with someone there</li>
  <li>if I were to look at your performance reviews from that job, what themes would I see in terms of areas for improvement?</li>
  <li>what was the worst decision you made there?</li>
</ul>

<p>These are all pretty standard interview questions. You might get self-aware candor or you might get a watered-down answer. But either way, you now have a nugget you can use on the reference calls. In my opinion, <em>this</em> is the best reason to ask those questions of candidates — not because you think their direct answers are particularly useful.</p>

<p>When you’re on the phone with the reference — Rachel — now you can say things like:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So Rachel, Carlos was very open with me — which I really appreciated — and told me about…</p>
  <ul>
    <li>… getting a bunch of feedback on his lack of attention to detail. Does that resonate with you?</li>
    <li>… the issue he had with Doug about the timeline for the mobile app launch. Do you remember that?</li>
    <li>… his decision to overrule his team on hiring someone. Do you remember how that went down?</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Once you say this, Rachel will very often open right up. She’ll feel the implicit permission to share her perspective on the situation from Carlos, since now she knows Carlos was already transparent with you about it.</p>

<p>Ideally, you can keep pushing down the rabbithole, showing more of your knowledge about it (which you got from Carlos):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>That’s very consistent with what he told me. It sounded like it might have caused a bit of a lingering issue, too… is that how you felt?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>People rarely want to break the news to you of a bad decision or a category of critical feedback. But once you’ve shown that the candidate themselves already broke it — and that you have an understanding of it — they are very often willing to fill in the gaps in a much more meaningful way.</p>

<p>This is, in my experience, by far the most effective tool on reference calls: grant the respondent implicit permission from the candidate to answer honestly. And the simple way to do that:</p>
<ol>
  <li>get a nugget about a negative situation or decision or critical feedback from the candidate</li>
  <li>tell the reference that the candidate told <em>you</em> about that already</li>
  <li>and ask their perspective and dig in deeper</li>
</ol>

<picture loading="lazy" class="vignette-image"><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/one-person-phone-400-c12d3809f.webp 400w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/one-person-phone-600-c12d3809f.webp 600w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/one-person-phone-800-c12d3809f.webp 800w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/one-person-phone-1000-c12d3809f.webp 1000w" type="image/webp" /><source srcset="/assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/one-person-phone-400-24f2564d6.png 400w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/one-person-phone-600-24f2564d6.png 600w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/one-person-phone-800-24f2564d6.png 800w, /assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/one-person-phone-1000-24f2564d6.png 1000w" type="image/png" /><img src="/assets/images/generated/useful-reference-calls/one-person-phone-800-24f2564d6.png" width="1899" height="535" /></picture>

<h2 id="tool-2-forced-quantitative-questions">Tool #2: forced quantitative questions</h2>

<p>People can come up with all sorts of innuendos, scapegoat answers, and ways to avoid the question when you ask them typical prompts (<em>“what were Carlos’s biggest areas for improvement?”</em>).</p>

<p>So one way to get the truth is to force a quantitative response with a well-structured question. Sometimes this is easy because there are quantitative individual results to measure (<em>“after he ramped, was Carlos in the top 25% of salespeople by quota attainment? Top 10%?”</em>) — but if that’s the case, you’ve probably already gotten that information from the candidate and are simply verifying it.</p>

<p>So how can you get <em>new</em> information in a quantitative format? I’ve found the best way is to transform a qualitative question into a quantitive one. Here are four questions I love (the first two are great direct interview questions too, not just reference call questions):</p>

<h3 id="scored-skills">Scored skills</h3>

<p>An example for an engineering manager you’re referencing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In this role, there are four skills we really care about: technical depth, recruiting/hiring, team management and leadership, and broader communication.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>If I gave you forty “points” and you had to allocate those for Carlos based on how good he is at each, how would you allocate them? That is, if you think he’s equally good at all four, he’d get 10 points each — but I imagine he’s likely better at some than others.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I love this question (again: great direct interview question too). It forces people to make tradeoffs and expose what someone is really good at — and what they’re less good at.</p>

<p>A typical answer comes after some clarification and back-and-forth — maybe it’s:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So for Carlos… maybe a 15 for technical depth, 10 for team management and leadership, and then… let’s say 9 for communication and 6 for recruiting. I feel bad only giving him a six there but I guess I need to make some tradeoffs!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This, of course, gives you more to dig in on with the reference or with the candidate.</p>

<h3 id="ranked-attributes">Ranked attributes</h3>

<p>This is somewhat similar to the “scored skills” question. I picked it up from <a href="https://grahamduncan.blog/whats-going-on-here/">What’s going on here, with this human?</a> (an excellent writeup from Graham Duncan on interviewing and referencing):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Three attributes I like to keep in mind are someone’s hunger, their humility, and how smart they are about people. If you were to force rank those for Jane from what she exhibits the most to least, how would you rank them?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I usually ask it slightly differently:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To succeed at this company / in this role, someone would need hunger, humility, and smarts about people. I think Carlos has all three — although tell me if you disagree! But, of course, everyone has a different balance of those attributes. So if you had to rank those three, from what Carlos exhibits most to least, how would you rank them?</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="endorsement-strength">Endorsement strength</h3>

<p>Another one from <a href="https://grahamduncan.blog/whats-going-on-here/">What’s going on here, with this human?</a>!</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How strong is your endorsement of Jane on a 1-10? (If they answer 7, say actually sorry 7s are not allowed, 6 or 8? If the answer is an 8, “What is in that two points?”)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think this question is great. But I’d inquire further no matter what they say:</p>

<p><strong>6 or below (rarely said):</strong> <em>“what would it have taken for them to make it to [number plus two]?”</em></p>

<p><strong>7:</strong> <em>“Sorry, 7s are not allowed. If forced to choose, would you go with 6 or 8?”</em></p>

<p><strong>8:</strong> <em>“Why an 8 not a 6? what is in that two points?”</em></p>

<p><strong>9:</strong> <em>“that’s amazing. I’m not surprised. What would it take for them to get to 10?”</em></p>

<p>If they say <em>“oh I just wouldn’t give a 10”</em> or something similar (they usually do), I say:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Hah, yep, I’m the same way. It would take something superhuman to hit a 10. For Carlos in his role… what would that have been?”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>10:</strong> <em>“incredible, although I’m not surprised — Carlos is clearly exceptional. I need to ask, though — would you ever give someone an 11?”</em></p>

<p>Then:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Rachel: “yes, I didn’t realize that was possible — it would be Carlos”</p>

  <p>You: “that’s great.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>or</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Rachel: “yes, I guess I could”</p>

  <p>You: “for Carlos to have hit that superhuman 11… what would that have taken?”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>or</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Rachel: “no, 10 is top of the line.”</p>

  <p>You: “does anyone else in a similar role get a 10 for you? If so I’d love to know how they and Carlos are <em>different</em> despite both being 10s.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="top-percentile">Top percentile</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Of all the engineering managers [or “engineers”, or “managers”, or whatever] that you’ve worked with in some capacity, where does Carlos fall percentile-wise? As in, top 50% of all engineering managers? Top 25%? Top 10%? Or what?”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>People will usually say <em>“top 10%”</em> (if they don’t, then you’ve collected very useful information!). Once they say top 10%, say:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>That’s great. I’m not surprised. What would it have taken Carlos to be in the top 1% you’ve ever worked with?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sometimes they will say <em>“oh wow, I didn’t realize top 1% was an option. He’s definitely there.”</em><label for="mn-1" class="margin-toggle">⊕</label>
<input type="checkbox" id="mn-1" class="margin-toggle" />
<span class="marginnote">
Occasionally you get a stickler who says “well they couldn’t be top 1% because I haven’t worked with that many people in that role.” If they say that, then just simply ask “fair enough — are they the best you’ve ever worked with in that role?”
</span></p>

<p>But more often, you’ll hear something like, <em>“oh, I mean he was really great. But to be top 1%… I guess maybe just been a little more communicative.”</em> And now you have a piece of information you can start digging deeper on.</p>

<p>Again: this question is all about forcing a quantification of a qualitative judgement, and works particularly well by not explicitly giving the respondent the option of the highest rating.</p>

<p>If Carlos was <em>really</em> top 1%, then they’ll say “oh more than top 10%… he’s the best ever.” And if not, they can still feel good about picking the highest choice presented (top 10%), but then when you follow up, they feel obligated to answer honestly about what would have made the candidate even better.</p>

<h2 id="what-next">What next?</h2>

<p>I’ll make another post later — and link it here — about other aspects of reference calls. How to reach out, backchannel vs. not, who to talk to, how to talk to the candidate about the results of the calls, the process on the call itself, etc.</p>

<p>But for now, I hope these tools for finding the truth are useful.</p>

<hr class="end-of-article-divider" />

<h2 class="no_toc">Looking for more to read?</h2>

<nav class="post-navigation">
  <div class="prev-post">
    
    <a href="/nile-sovereign-bookstore">
    
    <div class="post-nav-header"><i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-left post-nav-arrow"></i> Previous post</div>
    
    </a>
    
    
      <a href="/nile-sovereign-bookstore" class="external-link">Welcome to Nile: A Sovereign Bookstore<span class="home-article-external-link">(medium.com)</span></a>
    
  </div>
  <div class="next-post">
    <div class="post-nav-header">
        
        <a href="/minimum-effective-quantification">
        
        Next post <i class="fa-solid fa-arrow-right post-nav-arrow"></i>
        
        </a>
        
    </div>
    
      <a href="/minimum-effective-quantification">Minimum Effective Quantification</a>
    
  </div>
</nav>

<h3 class="no_toc" id="or-more-on-reference-calls">Or, more on reference calls:</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Who-Geoff-Smart/dp/0345504194">Who</a>, by Geoff Smart and Randy Street, is a great read on hiring, and has lots of good bits on references. Thanks to Matt Mochary for the recommendation many years ago.</p>

<p>I mentioned this earlier in the post: Graham Duncan’s article <a href="https://grahamduncan.blog/whats-going-on-here/">What’s going on here, with this human?</a> is excellent.</p>

<h3 class="no_toc">And for even more...<h3></h3>



<div>
    <p>Want to hear about new essays? Subscribe to my roughly-monthly <a href="https://andybromberg.substack.com">newsletter</a> recapping my recent writing and things I'm enjoying:</p>
    <div class="substack">
        <iframe src="https://andybromberg.substack.com/embed" width="480" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>
    </div>

    <p>And I'd love to hear from you directly: <a href="mailto:andy@andybromberg.com">andy@andybromberg.com</a></p>
</div>

</h3>]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few tricks and processes to make hiring reference calls informative and actionable.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/useful-reference-calls.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/useful-reference-calls.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Nile: A Sovereign Bookstore</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/nile-sovereign-bookstore" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Nile: A Sovereign Bookstore" /><published>2019-10-02T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-10-02T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/nile-sovereign-bookstore</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/nile-sovereign-bookstore"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/nile-sovereign-bookstore.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/nile-sovereign-bookstore.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Paying to be Bought: A Token Network Acquisition Blueprint</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/token-network-acquisition" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paying to be Bought: A Token Network Acquisition Blueprint" /><published>2018-06-05T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-06-05T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/token-network-acquisition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/token-network-acquisition"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/token-network-acquisition.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/token-network-acquisition.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Charter Currencies: A Future of Competitive Monetary Policy</title><link href="https://andybromberg.com/charter-currencies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Charter Currencies: A Future of Competitive Monetary Policy" /><published>2018-04-24T14:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-04-24T14:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://andybromberg.com/charter-currencies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andybromberg.com/charter-currencies"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Andy Bromberg</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/charter-currencies.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://andybromberg.com/assets/images/meta/posts/charter-currencies.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>